Okay, so in this video,
then we are going to
discuss a couple of common
procurement artifacts.
Now, artifact, remember,
is a document, and
it is a document that
we are trying to create.
It's a document that we are creating.
And in PIMBOC terminology,
in the PIMBOC guide
terminology, this would
be referred to as an output.
So these artifacts then would be an output
of procurement management.
Now, the first one I want to discuss is
this one called bid documents.
Now, there are three types of
bid documents that you need
to know about for the exam,
and those are these three here.
A request for information,
RFI, request for quote, RFQ,
and this one called an
RFP, a request for proposal.
Now, I'm sure, in fact,
I'm assuming most of
you have heard of an
RFP, request for proposal.
So an RFP is a bid document, but there are
other types as well.
You have the RFQ,
Request for Quote, which is
also known as an
invitation for bid, an IFB.
So you could see the term RFQ or IFB,
then basically mean the same thing.
Most of the time, though, you'll see RFQ.
Then you've got this one called the RFI
Request for Information.
So let's talk about the differences then
between these three
types of bid documents.
So first of all, RFI request for
information.
Now, as a name suggests,
request for information,
it's just for additional information.
Buy it and seller can be
submitting an RFI to the other
party, just asking for
some additional information.
And there's various different ways of
using an RFI.
It's not a fixed way.
There's various different ways.
It could be used before you send an
official RFP, right before the buyer sends
an official RFP to the
seller, or it could be used
after the buyer has
submitted an RFP to the seller.
So let me just give you an example then of
each one.
Now, in either case, though, it is used to
just obtain some general information about
the supplier themselves, about the vendor
themselves, or about their product or
service, and the whole
idea, the whole purpose
is to gain some additional familiarity.
So as a very simple example of an RFI
that's used before we send out an RFP,
this is used extensively by US government
agencies.
I mean, the other companies
use it as well, but I want
to give you an example of,
say, the US government agency.
There's many US government agencies.
So let's say they, you know, they're
determining this project.
Is this a viable project for us?
And if there is, what potential vendors
are out there?
So all the usual places where government
contractors are bidding on government
contracts, this government agency will
submit an RFI, a request for information.
And there's a whole bunch of questions on
there, right, which vendors then,
these potential sellers, will answer on a
voluntary basis.
So that if the government agency decides
this project valuable, is viable,
and they decide to go for a
bid, right, then they have a
list of vendors that they
can potentially reach out to.
These vendors have already answered a
whole bunch of questions that they had.
So that's one way of using an RFI,
a request for information.
They just have some
information and usually
with an RFI, there's no
money involved, right?
Or if there's no pricing, or if there is,
it's very, very high level pricing.
Now, sometimes it can be used once an RFP
has been submitted.
So the request for proposals,
the buyer has submitted
an RFP, a request for
a proposal to the seller.
The seller may have some additional
questions, right?
So they may send an RFI to the buyer for
some additional
information and vice versa.
The main thing about
an RFI is, again, literally
it is used for asking for
some information, right?
For either the buyer of the seller,
either party can send an RFI.
So let's talk about the
difference between the RFQ
request for quote and an
RFP request for proposal.
Remember, the RFQ, another name for that
is the IFB invitation for bid.
So what's the basic difference between the
two?
Now, the RFQ request for quote is focused
on the bottom line only.
It's focused on pricing.
So it's basically we know what we need.
It's a standard product.
and so we just want to know how much it's
going to cost.
So, for example, I want to purchase a
whole bunch of textbooks.
So for one of my classes I'm teaching,
you know, I want to purchase, say,
100 copies of this textbook, right,
even 1,000 copies of this textbook.
Well, there are a couple
of different supplies
out there that can supply
me with this textbook.
I want 100 copies or
1,000 copies, whatever
it is, you know, there's a few suppliers.
these textbooks, they're all the same.
I want to purchase this particular
textbook.
One textbook, right?
I mean, this particular textbook is not
going to be different.
It's one textbook, but I want 100 copies
of it.
So I just want to know the bottom line.
You know, different
vendors, different suppliers
can supply me with
this particular textbook.
Well, how much is it going to cost me?
What discounts are you going to give?
So I will send them an RFQ.
request for quote.
An RFP, on the other
hand, focus as more on
the needs and
expectations of the customer.
You need to get some
requirements from the customer
before you can actually
give some kind of quote.
So again, a simple example.
I have my own training company.
If somebody asks me,
can you give me a quote
for some project
management training in-house?
Well, immediately I can't give them a coat
like that, right, I have to ask some
questions, not in the least, you know,
how many days?
Well, first of all, what kind of project
management training do you want?
Is it PMP training?
Is it some other kind of project
management training?
At how many days, how many people,
which location, right?
Then I'm going to go into the more of the
needs and requirements, needs and
expectations, going to understand the need
for the training, right?
So then I can customize the training for
them and so on and so forth.
So I will need to get their
requirements, right, before, at
least some high-level requirements
before I can submit a quote.
So they would then send me an RFP,
a request for a proposal.
So that's a basic difference then between
the RFQ and the RFP.
With the RFQ, it is one standard product.
We know exactly what we want, right?
And, you know, we want
a whole bunch of these
standard products, so
it's based on pricing only.
Whereas with the RFP,
you need to go into more
than needs and
expectations of the customer.
Now, another common
artifact is this one called the
Statement of Work, the
Procurement Statement of Work.
And the statement of work
for services is known as a
term of reference, but
basically it's used the same way.
And a statement of work is a legal document,
right, becomes part of the contract.
And it is just basically
documenting what the
project is about, what
this procurement is about.
Now, let's just take a step back and think
about where we are.
We're in procurement.
What is the procurement?
In a procurement, we are the customer.
Remember, we are the customer.
And the vendor is doing the work for us.
So we have this project, we have this big
project that we're doing.
A portion of this project, we have decided
to outsource it.
And so this portion of the project that
we've decided to outsource for that
portion of the project, we are the
customer.
So we are going to give our requirements
to the vendor.
From those requirements, we're going to
come up with the scope, the schedule,
the budget, all baseline.
And that will all be documented in the
procurement statement of work,
which will be signed off and it will
become part of the contract.
So the procurement statement of work then
is a legal document.
So the statement of work
then is developed from our
original scope statement
for the overall project, right?
So this is our project.
So this whole project, right, has already
been baselined, right?
So we've already been baselined.
And so it's going to be developed the
scope statement then.
It's going to be developed from the
baseline, right?
And we're creating the scope statement.
And what's it going to contain?
Right, well, all the work that needs to be
performed, right, any standards that need
to be abided by, right, the budget,
the timeline, and so and so forth.
So it basically contains as much detailed
information as possible because here's a
legal document, and it will become part of
the contract.
Now, who writes a statement of work,
is it the buyer or the seller?
Well, generally the buyer
will write it, but sometimes
the seller can write it,
sometimes it's a joint effort.
But whoever writes a statement of work,
it has to be written in sufficient detail
so that both buy it and seller
can have a good understanding
of what is to be delivered,
what is not to be delivered.
So these are just a couple of additional
common artifacts, right, additional common
documents that you need to know regarding
procurement.